Hello all, today we are going to look at
what MCP, model context protocol, actually
is.
We all know MCP is a way of connecting our
data and tools to AI applications.
But if we were asked what MCP exactly is
or why it is a must for AI application
these days or how it is helping engineers
and product owners to simplify the
connection, not many of us can answer the
question clearly, right?
In this video, I will use one simple
example the whole way through, like a
support agent for an online store and we
will look at it from architecture's point
of view, step-by-step.
In this video, we are going to run through
five different topics.
Number one, how AI agents are built before
MCP even existed.
And number two, what are all the
drawbacks?
What are all the disadvantages we add with
that approach?
And number three, what MCP is?
Why MNC came into existence?
And number four, what are all the
different benefits we get out of it?
And finally, we will look at why the name
model context protocol.
We will go through word by word and
understand what each term within the name
model context
protocol is.
So before we go in detail about it, we
need to understand an example.
So let's say you are a backend engineer of
a company which owns Amazon like
e-commerce website.
And let's say the website has project
management API, order management API,
payment and refund API, or notification
API, which is serving your website, okay?
And the users are demanding you to create
an AI agent which can answer questions for
this website.
And that is our example.
So we are going to build this agent
together and we are going to build it
without MCP in it.
So how the agents look like?
So usually the agent looks like with two
main components.
One is support agent, which is like the
actual code of the agent.
And the LLM can be chat GPT or Gemini or
any large language model.
So the user asked the question in and it
goes to support agent and the support
agent asks LLM and LLM gives with the user
friendly answer and that is written to the
user.
So in this case, if the user is asking
like, where is my order, it goes to LLM.
And in this case, it doesn't have that
kind of knowledge because order has to
come from order management API and it is
not attached.
So it doesn't have that information to
return back.
So as an engineer, now you're going to add
order management API capability to your
support agent.
And what you're doing, you are integrating
the order management API to your agent.
And you're adding the instruction to your
LLM on how to use it, when to use it and
what input to send.
And also, you're updating the support
agent to how to request this API and make
a call to this API and get the response
back.
So let's say you have set that up.
And now the user is asking, where is my
order now?
So what is going to happen is more like
the agent is going to ask the LLM, what
should I do?
And the LLM has all the instruction now.
So the moment it receives a question like,
where is my order?
The instruction to LLM says like, you need
to call order management API.
So LLM is going to send the response back
to the agent saying that call order
management API and pause this already.
Now agent calls the order management API
directly and API returns the raw order
data.
Agent extracts the status status and sends
it to LLM and LLM responds to the user
saying your order is being packed for
delivery.
So this is how the flow looks like for one
question.
So now the user is impressed and user asks
another question.
Can I find a product in blue color?
And now again, the agent is going to ask
LLM now I received a question like, can I
find the product in blue color?
And what should I do?
And the instruction doesn't say anything
about the product details, all it has is
all the instructions about the order
details, but this is about the product and
no details available.
So in this case, the LLM is going to
return saying sorry, I'm unable to answer
the question.
So how do you improve your support agent?
You can improve your support agent by
adding the project management API.
So you have gone through the same process.
Now you have updated the instruction to
include details for product management API
as well.
So the LLM has all the information of both
API's available for it to call and receive
answers.
And you also upgraded your support agent
so that it can call order management API
or product management API when it is
required.
Now the user asked the question, can I get
this in blue?
And again, the question is sent from agent
to LLM.
And LLM response saying it follows the
instruction.
And it says like, okay, now you need to
call project management API and pass the
color as blue.
So agents build the JSON request and cause
the product management API API returns a
raw data and this is extracted and sent to
LLM and LLM puts in a nice friendly
response to the user.
So now your support agent can answer
questions on orders and it can also answer
questions on products, right?
Good.
So next, the user wanted to know if he can
get a refund for his product.
So in this case, a refund means you need
to have access to payment and refund API,
which is not there.
So unfortunately, at this time, the LLM is
going to respond saying sorry, I'm unable
to answer the question.
So again, the engineer had to go through
another upgrade to your support agent.
So now he's adding one more payment and
refund API to it, updating the
instructions to the LLM and
updating the support agent to integrate
this new payment and refund API.
So this is a working example.
And we know this is going to work.
And this is how exactly it was working
before AMCP comes into existence.
When it all works, what is the problem?
The problem is it doesn't scale well.
There are three major drawbacks that shows
as soon as we have gone through second
version or third version or including
second API or third API to the agent.
And what are those drawbacks?
The first drawback is the APIs are tightly
coupled now to the agent, which means
every time you upgrade the agent, you're
adding more code base to the agent.
So which means when the support agent was
V1, it was tightly coupled to order API.
And when the support agent upgraded to V2,
it has details of both order API and
product API.
And V3, it has details of order API,
product API, and payment API.
And it is all tightly coupled.
So in case if you wanted to remove the
support agent and add another financial
agent, you have to do everything from the
scratch.
Everything you can reuse it, right?
And the second drawback is it contains
APIs are low level details.
So every time you wanted to integrate an
API into your agent, you need to, you need
to give instructions about inputs and
output schemas, passing, error handling,
retries, and you need to literally do all
the plumbing work within the support
agent.
Technically, the support agent should be
as simple as making a call and getting the
response.
But unfortunately, here we are directly
integrating the API, which means all the
plumbing goes into the support agent.
And the third drawback is it makes the
agent more and more complex every time.
So the first version was easy.
But the second version has two API
integrations, which means it was
moderately complex.
And the third version, it got difficult
because it is integrating three different
APIs, which means it has all the details
of three different APIs now.
And there is no ceiling for this.
The more APIs you add, the more data
source you add, it's going to get more and
more complicated.
So that's where the MCP comes into
picture.
So what is MCP?
Let's quickly go through what MCP is.
And we will try to build the same support
agent using MCP now.
So MCP, in very simple terms, it is a
common communication language that is
built between I mean, it is used between
LLM powered application, and the tools we
want them to use to answer questions.
So it's as simple as you have LLM powered
apps on one side, and tools on the other
side.
And you're going to use this MCP to
communicate between those two different
components.
We are taking the same example again,
again, you have this user and you have the
support agent, and this time, the support
agent, it is going to make call to
Ecommerce MCP server.
So instead of it directly integrating to
the API, it is going to make call to the
Ecommerce MCP server, and it is going to
get the details back.
So this is more like a client server
architecture, which means you will have
MCP client sitting attached to the support
agent.
And MCP client is going to call the
Ecommerce server, and Ecommerce server has
all different set of tools.
And how this architecture works.
So whenever the support agent is initiated
or initialized, the MCP client discovers
the menu of tools, it is going to make a
quick call to know all the tools that is
available within the MCP service.
So in this example, it has get orders,
order details, order status, get products,
product details, etc.
and the Ecommerce MCP server is going to
have the instruction the details on what
each tool does.
So the support agent doesn't have anything
when it is initialized.
And the moment the Ecommerce MCP server is
attached to it, it made a call, it asked
to return the list of tools, and it also
comes with the instruction.
So by the time the support agent read all
the tools available, it also knows where
in which case which tool to use.
So let's take this example.
So where is my order now?
So when the user asks, where is my order
now?
Now first when the agent is initialized,
it is asking like, give me all your tools.
And by the time it has got all the details
of the tools, and also the instructions on
when to use each tool.
So now when the question is asked, the
agent knows it pick it has to pick order
details and calls it.
The server replacement order status
already in the form of LLM that it can
read.
So whatever outcome, whatever output that
MCP server produces, it is in the same
format which the LLM can easily
understand, and directly post it to the
user, it doesn't have to go through a JSON
formatted message or good bunch of details
that it has to filter out to find the
details, it already has all the
information in a simple text format that
it can take it from the Ecommerce MCP
server and directly post it to the user.
And one more big advantage is you don't
have to build the MCP server on your own
every time.
So for example, in our case, we had four
different API's product management API,
order management API, and payment and
refund API, and notification API, let's
say.
So let's say you're using a tool called
Stripe for payment and refunds and slack
for messaging and notification.
These are well known products for payment
refunds and messaging and notification,
right?
So most probably they have their own
official MCP server published for their
products.
So on that case, your support agent can be
as simple as you're creating your own
company or the MCP server, wanting to get
product and orders details.
But to do the payment and refunds, you can
use Stripe MCP, and for messaging and
notification, you can use Slack MCP.
And these days, each and every major
software company, they are coming up with
their own set of MCP servers, which you
can directly use it within your system.
Why is this worth?
What are all the benefits that this is
bringing?
So what are all the advantages you get by
using MCP server instead of you directly
integrating one of the API to your ISE
agent?
The first one is reusability.
So in our example, so far, what we have
done is we have the support agent, which
is making a call to e-commerce MCP server
to get the details back.
So you have a dedicated e-commerce MCP
server.
And this can not only be used by support
agent, but it can also be used by
different agents in the future.
For example, in the future, if you have
finance agent that it needs to use the
e-commerce MCP server, it just it is as
simple as just plug and play.
And the future, if you're going to add one
more executive or manager agent, and if it
requires order details or product details,
it is as simple as plug and play.
You don't have to make any changes.
All you have to do is to do the
configuration to call this MCP server by
using the URL hdpse.com slash MCP.
And that's it.
You have it there.
So many agents can use the same e-commerce
MCP server.
The next one is it is loosely coupled.
So in this example, we have this
e-commerce MCP server.
Just in case in the future, if you have
another competitive e-commerce MCP server
e-commerce product that you wanted to use,
you can easily swap it just switch it.
So in this example, as you can see here,
it has moved to Amazon e-commerce MCP
server.
So previously, it was like the company
owned one.
And you can easily switch it to other
e-commerce server.
There's no like hot wired connection
between the agents and MCP servers.
It is loosely coupled.
And it gives immense advantage for anybody
doing enterprise architecture.
And the third advantage is the
scalability.
So you got like five different tools
within your MCP servers in the future.
If you want to add more tools like
introducing update product, which will
update the product or introducing delete
product, which will delete the product,
you can just simply upgrade the MCP
servers and the rules and regulations are
automatically populated and it is ready to
use on all the agents now.
So you don't have to do the code changes
on any of the support agents or finance
agents.
That is all completely fixed.
All you have to do is upgrade your MCP
server and deploy it.
And it is all readily available to be
used.
The new tools also are readily available
to be used by support agent, finance
agent, or manager agents for that.
So these are all massive, massive, big
advantages that MCP server brings in when
it is used with our support agent.
Why the name model context protocol?
Three words and definitely each one has
its own meaning that makes the term model
context protocol.
First, we will see what is protocol,
protocol is nothing but a shared set of
rules for correct communication.
A protocol is a set of rules and standard
procedures that guides correct behavior or
technical
communication, for example, HTTP.
So HTTP is widely used protocol between
the web client and the web server.
So web clients, if you have a web server
like google.com, and if it has used HTTP
protocol to expose the screen in HTML
format, then Chrome can access it, Firefox
can access it, Edge can access it.
You don't have to do a separate code for
your web application to run in Chrome
browser or Firefox browser, right?
That's what the protocols advantage is.
It follows the same set of rules that is
applicable for any browser.
And you develop one application and one
web application and that is readily
accessible by any browsers.
Similarly, MCP is another protocol.
So it comes with a set of rules or
standard procedures that anybody wanted to
do it so that the
communication is stable.
And you can use it between any AI models
and MCP server tools.
That's protocol for us.
And what is model?
So the word model, model context protocol,
built specifically means this MCP is built
specifically for AI models.
So AI models like GPT, Gemini, or cloud
powered app.
So model is designed for AI models and it
is not for web applications or mobile
apps.
APIs are written for human written code to
request and retrieve JSON with MCP.
The LLM itself first discovers all the
available tools, understand the
capabilities and decide which one to use.
So that's where the model comes into
picture.
And finally, what is context?
Context is more like memory across
multiple steps.
So if you notice when you're using chat
GPT or any agent for that matter, you can
see I want to refund it.
The it is the order the user asked about
30 seconds ago.
But in this sentence, it doesn't have any
value.
But just because it has a memory, and it
can remember what is the discussion about
and which order is currently being
discussed now, when the user says I want
to refund it.
It knows the it in the sentence, it means
the order which is currently in
discussion.
So to put it simply, LLM powered app, it
contains its own LLM.
And it has this MCP client, which is used
to connect to MCP servers.
And the context storage, it's a memory
that holds the tools details, and the
instructions of when the tools to use.
And it has a memory to remember some of
the history.
So that's why the context comes into
picture.
And it is called model context protocol.
So to put it simply, MCP is a protocol
designed specifically for AI models.
And it maintains context across multi step
interaction within tools.
So there is one topic or one method that
comes into play every time is MCP
replacement for the API.
No, it is not MCP is not a replacement for
the API.
MCP gives AI models and applications a
common interface, and a simplified LLM
friendly response.
But it sits on top of the API, it doesn't
replace it API is used by human written
code to make a call and get the response
back, but the MCP is more like it will, it
is a
communication protocol between the AI
model and the MCP server.
So in this example, as you can see, MCP
server looks more LLM friendly, like it
will have the concurrent type equals text,
and text is your orders being packed for
delivery.
But if it is a raw API response, it will
be more like already order name data for
the status, etc, etc.
So MCP is definitely not a replacement of
API API will be still used across multiple
web services and websites to make a call
and get the data back.
But MCP comes into play when you're doing
a agent or a application that needs access
to the data sources, which is available
via MCP.
I hope that gives you a quick overview of
how MCP comes into picture and plays an
important role between connecting a agents
with other data tools.
And the next video, we will try to do a
hands on coding session where we will
create a agent and create a MCP server and
we will try to connect this MCP server
into our agent and give it a try.
Until then, thank you very much for
watching and I'll see you in the next
video.